software engineering radio episode 102
relational databases
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our website for supporting the hot
rod
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio my name is
Fran cope today on the microphone with
me is our no hacer I don't know hi
everybody
so our topic today are relational
databases I don't know why don't you
explain in a brief overview what are
relational databases sure
well relational databases are basically
big boxes in which you can store any
kind of data in a transactional way
there's another episode on transactions
which goes into all the details of what
transactional storage means but a
relational database means you have one
big container you can put anything you
want into the container and you have
queries to retrieve the data to look at
it they're reliable they're robust
they're scalable they're highly
available and have all these nice
non-functional properties that are so
useful in today's enterprise world and
embedded and wherever so relational
databases basically are places to store
data ok and so why is that topic
interesting for me or important for me
as a developer or architect that is
really a good question I mean databases
are so present in most projects nowadays
that many people feel they have an
understanding of them people think I
know what databases do I know how to
write to select I know how to write an
insert so why should I go deeper into
relational databases I know all about
them and actually I think this is one of
the problems that people tend to think
they know about relational databases
many applications are designed nowadays
with databases as an afterthought you
design the application logic and you
have object relational mapping and then
you sort of feel ok I can plug in any
database and it's going to work and
basically it is not going to work really
well unless you understand how databases
work internally because you run into all
kind of performance issues scalability
issues and so I think it's a good idea
for developers and is
the architects to be familiar with the
persistence layer technology and
languages and not only the middle tier
languages like Java or C sharp or
whatever I guess we should mention in
the in the overview that schema design
and writing database applications is not
scope of that episode right right yeah
very good point
schema design is stuff enough for an
entire other episode which we might or
might not wear in a later time and also
designing application as a whole it's
out of scope this is really just about
um databases per se that brings to my
mind an anecdote I heard about Kent Beck
who said you should not start with
relational database per se you should
not say before you know what the
application should do I need relational
database you should consider the
alternatives in good extreme program
manner start with the simplest possible
thing which usually is file storage and
then build on that if you need something
added this is sort of a weird approach
oftentimes you do know that you need a
relational database but it illustrates
that there are alternatives I mean you
can always store data and files or if
it's read-only data read data from files
which is often a good alternative in at
least for some kinds of applications and
then there's other kinds of databases
like object-oriented databases or
hierarchical databases so relational
databases are not the only solution it's
good to have the whole range of
solutions in scope but relational
databases are the most widely used
technologies to store data and they're
basically all over the place you have
them in huge applications that that
store many kind many rows of data large
amounts Amazon or Ebay or whatever but
you also have them in very small
settings there are relational databases
nowadays that are used in embedded
devices so you have a whole wide range
of different technologies of different
products the underlying technology of
relational databases is the same this
brings another thing to my mind most
database vendors want to say that their
database is the best the biggest or
whatever so they all bring their own
kinds of benchmarks and my sequel I
think has the largest installed base
which means the largest
number of websites that uses my sequel
which is quite probable quite likely
because they they're used by many it's
very small online shops and sites
whereas db2 or Oracle or maybe Microsoft
secret server I'm not up to date and
it's very hard to check anyway say they
have the largest amount of data or the
largest number of rows or the largest
amounts of money that are managed so you
have a wide range of ways to say I'm the
biggest database vendor in the world and
so if you have here some kind of
statistics that way don't take them too
seriously you cannot check them anyway
and every vendor has his own way his own
statistics that lets him look good which
brings me to a very important thing here
we're going to mention different
products and different vendors but we
we're not paid by any of them and we're
not going to say this is a good database
this is bad database so whatever we say
about them many of them there are many
different vendors many different
products and we're not going to endorse
any of them in special way before you
mentioned embedded databases and so
maybe you can explain what is an
embedded database what I was talking
about is a database that is small enough
to run in an embedded device which
basically means it has very small memory
footprint and very small disk footprint
and has real time characteristics but
probably will not scale very well which
makes it applicable for for small for
small devices embedded devices and then
there's another kind of databases which
are known as in-memory databases what
are their specific characteristics well
in-memory databases are sort of exotic
in the overall landscape they're mainly
useful for testing purposes there are
certain databases that run entirely in
memory and keep all the data in memory
which makes them very fast and means
that the database driver usually is the
anti replica the entire implementation
of the database which means you can if
can start a database put data into it in
a test without much installation
overhead which makes them very useful
for development but usually not for
production use okay so I guess that's
all for the introduction
I think we can now start with the
relational paradigm so what is the
relational paradigm okay relational
databases
I mean relational sort sort of sounds
like mathematics and it is actually
there is a whole mathematical theory
behind it that every all data is taught
in relations and everything is relation
which is sort of nice has an aesthetic
feeling to it but it all breaks down to
relational databases means everything is
a table with rows and columns so the
land the language to to deal with
relational databases is sequel
structured query language there used to
be all kinds of products in the 80s with
all the different languages and dialects
but it was standardized way back it's
standardized quite well and this
paradigm means all data is stored in
rows and columns
it is exists by retrieving rows and
columns several tables can be joined
together and to make different tables
with rows and columns and everything is
a row and column it's the strength of
this paradigm is that it's very simple
everyone can understand it and it's the
image of putting data in a table is
well-known to many people it's sort of
you can catch it down on whiteboard or a
piece of paper and storing data in
tables and columns is so widely used
nowadays that it sort of feels like it's
the only way to store data but there are
other approaches especially hierarchical
data um which means you have one root
element and from that you have the data
this contain in it that's basically the
XML way of storing data XML is the
modern technology that stores data in a
hierarchical way you have one root
element and children you have a tree and
you have arm it differed all kinds of
you have a whole paradigm whole group of
databases hierarchical databases that
were invoked before relational databases
came along in the 80s they are still
used sometimes and you have object or a
databases that are sort of an arbitrary
graph you have opted an object here
object there an object over there
and they have pointers all over the
place which makes them very different
but relational databases store things in
tables and rows and columns which means
that there is no concept of a reference
between different tables you have a
table with persons you have a table with
addresses and they have something to do
with each other because the every dress
belongs to a person but there's no
pointer per se but the way to match data
is to use a drawing you have column in
the person table that identifies the
person which is called primary key and
you have a column in the address table
which identifies an address which is
called the primary key of the address
table then you have another column in
the person table that holds the holds a
value that is also a primary key in the
address table and then you match those
and say if the foreign key in one table
matches the primary key another table
those two should be matched together
it's called a drawing their special
simple syntax for that there's inter
inner joins outer joins we're going to
go into those in a different episode on
sequel and um but the key thing to
remember here is you can navigate any
way you can start all over the place and
the query language means the whole
contents of the database are one huge
pool of data in a way like everything is
in one big global variable and everyone
can access it you there's no starting
point you can start anywhere and move by
joining all over the place all through
the data which is the special thing
about relational databases it's
different from all the other paradigms
that are sort of um that have explicit
links or hierarchies in rational
database you can start anywhere and have
any kinds of conditions and move all
over the place in any way you like which
makes it very very powerful for queries
for arbitrary queries um and some of the
queries that are or if you have queries
that you use more frequently you can
store those queries in views which is
basically a table without explicit
a storage it's a select query that you
store with a give name and since the
results of any select career our table
we use look like a table you can access
them directly and there are
optimizations behind those they're
called materialized views some vendors
have them which means that the that they
actually cache the results of the query
and some databases even allow writing to
views which is which is special it's
useful in some cases again everything is
a table and these the self similarity is
one of the strengths of sequel so these
these kind of queries that pull together
data from all kinds of all place of the
database and retrieve them and make them
available in the form of a table those
this is sort of the the basic meat of
querying relational database um
and storing data in rows and columns
with using insert or update but there is
a whole you wide range of syntax built
on top of that like inner selects you
can select data and happen to temporary
table that is used as part of the query
somewhere else and you can have report
kind of thing like grouping data adding
things retrieving the maximum the
minimum value sorting data sorting data
exactly and there's a huge range of
syntax in sequel you have case
statements you have if you have string
concatenation really really cool
powerful stuff we're going to go into
that in the sequel episode but here yeah
that the menu the key thing is
everything is a table so all this syntax
um all these special things are built on
tables and retreat material tables and
as you may have noticed I think the
relational paradigm is a really
beautiful paradigm I love this paradigm
because it's so simple and yet so
extremely powerful the Select clauses
that is the queries in sequel are a very
expressive side effect free functional
language for those of you who love to go
into a language theory they're sort of
sort of self-contained self similar
the underlying concept is very very
simple and well the downside is as with
so many simple paradigms the performance
is intrinsically limited you are free to
move around all over the place but since
there isn't are no explicit pointers all
kinds of lookups must be done by the
database engine at runtime which tends
to makes it slower and there's the whole
issue of indexes to deal with this to
give the data but to tell the database
which kind for which kind of queries to
prepare a cache that is maintained
whenever data has changed which makes
the lookups faster this is one of the
things that is very important to
understand in order to write well
performing and well-designed databases
which means that which goes well way
beyond the object-oriented paradigm of
the middle tier this is something that
is in the persistence tier and you
really need to understand how the
database works how your product works
what kind of looks up lookups your
queries do and then you can understand
what kind of indexes can be used to tune
this and you need to balance this
because I'm creating index if you have
an index it means anytime you change the
data in the tables the index must be
updated so actually an index can make
the database slower there are special
columns well first of all every column
has a data type of course there are
built-in data types basically you the
built-in data types you have in any
language and you expect from other
languages that is into integer numbers
of different precision you have fixed
point numbers of arbitrary of different
precision you have strings and you have
date and timestamp and that's basically
is there is no boolean value no boolean
type which means you have to emulate
that using using a number usually and
you have special types for for storing
huge amounts of data
they're called blobs binary large
objects or C lobs character hot objects
strings and database are limited in
length
which means there's a max maximum length
which is important for for performance
optimizations inside the database but
you can have arbitrary size objects
blobs and co-ops it's good to have them
but they have huge negative impact on
the performance so you tend to avoid
them unless you need them which is sort
of true of most things there's special
columns I mentioned them primary keys
and foreign keys primary keys means you
have you need to have one or more
columns to identify every row in a table
there there must be unique in order to
have this property of being able to
provide a way to look up data and there
are identifiers there is there different
philosophies there one traditional
approach was to use business values as
identifiers and this well for example
for books you could use the ISBN number
or for employees the employee number
that is printed on their company ID card
or whatever so you can have primary keys
that are represented in the real world
that are actually accessible that are
visible outside the database that have a
meaning outside the database and well
this is or the social security number in
the United States is a very popular
primary key used for people so the thing
is that the primary key has to be unique
within one database table right yes the
primary key must be unique inside every
database table and this leads to a
problem if you use if you use business
values as primary keys because for
example Social Security numbers they are
unique yes but in cases of identity
theft you may have to assign a different
social security number to the same
person so one person can have two Social
Security numbers at different times or
ISBN numbers are supposed to be unique
but there are exotic cases when they are
not unique or you might want to recycle
company ID cards so that a person who
left also after after one employee left
the company let's say after two years
you give these you assign the same
employee number to a different employee
because you want to reuse the ID card so
using these kinds of externally visible
values as primary keys is potentially
problematic because it is very difficult
to change primary keys to primary key
values of rows so the preferred approach
today the modern approach is and has
been for quite a while too to use
synthetic primary keys that is to have
an algorithm that calculates a unique
value forever for every year odor that
is added and this ID is used internally
only it's not visible outside the
database so you can assign it you can
manage it you can use it without anyone
else caring which means there's no there
are no external forces that lead to the
problems that I have just sketched so
are there any special strategies to
generate the primary keys yeah there are
quite a few strategies out there there
is sequence numbers which is a
proprietary but widely used feature of
different databases which means the
database provides a way to access
automatically incremented numbers there
is the special case of an auto increment
column which means the database
increments or assigns a new primary key
to any road that is inserted those are
useful at first sight they have the
problem that the primary key of a newly
inserted row is just inside the database
and it's not in the application so the
application needs to access the the
database a second time to retrieve the
primary key that was just assigned some
databases have special means to do this
and one lookup but anyway they are
proprietary from non-standard extensions
of the sequel standard so you become
very dependent on a specific database if
you use those another way is to have a
table in which the application itself
keeps track of primary keys and there
are quite sophisticated algorithms out
there called high-low that with
our which work in a cluster which means
their work when different kind different
applications access the same database
and one access to this storage primary
key storage table retrieves a whole
bunch of a range of numbers and that can
afterwards being assigned by the
application there are tricky issues for
example what happens if different
different kinds of applications access
the database they all needs to use the
same strategy to assign primary key
values to newly inserted rows another
issue to keep in mind is if you
replicate the database you need to make
sure that both sides of the replication
have compatible ideally identical ranges
for the primary keys so that they will
not there will not be a mismatch that so
that they won't run through the problem
that one database assigns a primary key
value that was already assigned by the
other one those are things to keep in
mind if you if you decide on a primary
key strategy okay so now I have primary
keys how can I use this primary keys to
make sure that I can reference another
element from another table you're
talking about foreign keys now those are
the the code just artery columns that
are in other tables and want to well
sort of drawing these two tables
together actually they're not really
keys they're just normal columns let's
get back to this example of persons and
addresses a typical way to do this would
have would be to add a person ID column
to the address table and store the
primary key of a person in this person
ID column of the address table so that
when you take a look at the address you
can you know which person this address
belongs to you can do this without
having without using the database
feature of a foreign key and well there
are reasons to actually not use this
foreign key feature because it has a
little performance impact mainframe
databases mainframe applications tend to
turn
switch that off for production if you
use the foreign key feature of the
database you have the additional benefit
of having the database check consistency
that is the database ensures that in the
that the value in the foreign key column
is the valid is an actually existing
value in the primary key column of the
reference table which leads us nicely to
constraints oh yeah good point
um this is just one example of the
constraints the databases support mmm
the most general kind of constraint is
you can have arbitrary boolean
expressions on the contents of a table
as a constraint the called check
constraints and they're part of the
sequel standard it's one of the rare
used features few developers know this
or use this and the the benefit is that
you have a self documenting database
schema and well obviously the database
is sort of it's sort of like designed by
contract the database checks at run time
if what the application gives it is
valid um this is of course no
replacement for checking in the
application as well because the
application should only attempt to
insert valid data but the database make
sure that only valid data gets into the
database and it's sort of a catch-all
hmm sort of like a second lock on the
world to make sure data integrity is
maintained this is what's behind these
constraints they are enforced at runtime
while the application tries to write
into the database and if the cap
Legation tries to write data into the
database that violates this constraint
an exception is thrown or any way the
database returns an error and most
importantly does not check it does not
insert the data into the database or
update the data a special case of this
constraint is not now which is probably
the constraint most developers are
familiar with just means that a
particular column must not be now and
there's another concept in databases
which is also not part of the standard
but it's um quite widely used and so
useful that is triggers and it's
different from constraints constraints
are a condition that is checked and if
it's violated the the modification is
rejected
as triggers our code that is executed in
the database and that is triggered by by
some kind of change so for example you
can have a change after a row was
inserted you can have some stored
procedure we'll get to those later
that is executed whenever data was
modified you can perform some kinds of
constraints checks there but they are
more powerful
the downside is they're not standardized
I guess that's it for the relational
paradigm now let's have a look to
performance what kind of performance
aspects do we have in relational
databases okay yeah well that's a huge
topic as I mentioned the database the
relational paradigm means that you do
not have a single starting point and you
don't do not have predefined paths
through the database so whenever you
look up a row in a single column you
have some kind of where clause so you
have some kind of condition and retrieve
only those rows that are met by this
condition which means that naively
implemented the database engine would
have to go through every row in the
table and check the condition and then
call and doing this collect all those
four which meet the condition this is
called a full table scan and it's
obviously really really bad really
expensive so yeah it's sort of the worst
case in terms of performance because the
database must read any every other data
of the entire table from the from the
disk and look at it so um the what you
can do is create indexes which means he
give the database hints or well tell the
database to create a cache sort of a
mapping between certain values in the
inner condition and the rows that meet
these criteria the simplest index is the
is an index on a single column typically
the primary key so that if you say I
want to have the row two
of the person table with a person ID 5
the database will not have to go through
the entire table but it has a lookup
table that starts with E that that is
sorted by the primary key and it looks
up where on the disk the row with the ID
5 is stored and the new trips this
there's a whole science behind that
research going into how to implement
these efficiently the key idea behind
implementations today is trees ideally
the databases will want to keep these
indexes in memory which makes lookup
very fast but for big databases it's not
possible to keep these indexes in memory
and the second best thing is to have
some kind of binary tree some kind of
easily in indexable structure which on
disk which makes it fast to look up on
disk um you can have indexes that span
several columns those are much more
specific in their usefulness than single
column indexes because they are they
only helpful if you have queries that
have exactly this combination of columns
in their conditional in the where clause
can you give an example on that well
let's say we want persons with an income
and range of between thirty and forty
thousand dollars a year and we want to
have those with the job title of manager
then we would have a select clause in
which the income column and the job
title column are part of the where
clause and the database without an index
the database page would have to scan the
entire person table to retrieve all
these all the employees that meet
criteria in those two columns but if we
have an index for these two columns then
in combination then the database can use
this combined index to retrieve on the
only rows that match the criteria
without going through the entire table
it's much faster okay these things can
become really really complicated
um if you have inner selects and
complicated joins and the best approach
to this kind of performance tuning
because well indexes our performance
tuning is to write an application with
few indexes in the beginning and then do
measurements find out what what kind of
queries take up most of the time and
then find out why finding out what kind
of queries take up most of the time is
just to normal profiling databases have
tools for that you can even do that in
the middle tier if you want to because
because in the middle you know what kind
of previous goes out and can measure
that but finding out what takes the
takes up the time is more tricky and in
order to understand that database
products have tools that provide you
with what is called a query plan mmm the
query plan is let me start a different
point if you send a query to the
database the database engine parses this
query and tries to optimize it tries to
turn it around this way and that to make
best use the best use it can of indexes
there are many different ways of
approaching this it's often a good idea
to first do is um throw away most of the
data if you have two conditions one of
them throws away most of the data
another let's in most it's good idea to
first throw away most of the data and
then look at these small resulting set
and then go through that a second time
there are all kinds of different tricks
and it's very there's much research
going to that and after this this is
called the optimizer the optimizer step
and the output of the optimizer is the
query plan the optimizer um the query
plan tells the database to move full
table scan on this table and use index
and do this index or another table and
so um it spells out the details of how
the database accesses data and it's
obviously this is very specific the
tooling and the things the database does
are very specific to the different
products but it's definitely worth
looking at in the documentation of the
database engine to to get on our
standing of this and play around with it
a little because that's the approach to
get
efficient database applications to
tuning the database because only if you
understand where the performance is
spent you know which indexes are useful
otherwise you'll end up with lots of
indexes and still most of them won't be
used and you'll still have some gaps so
analyzing the create of the performance
with by looking at the query planes is
the way to go I also heard that you can
even run into that locks with indexes do
you want to say something about that
yeah that's yeah there's a story behind
that in a project I won suppose there
were very many indexes on a database
I'm not going to tell you which product
is because it might reflect badly on
this and it might happen with other
products by but the indexes are stored
in tables internally in this database
product and so well when when a row was
inserted or modified in a table all the
indexes month needs to be armed to be
updated and this led to situation an
exotic situation but still there it was
um we're different were concurrent
modifications to the table caused a
deadlock in the updates to the to the
index tables which meant that
performance went extremely down the hill
sometimes erratically we figured that
out looking at the query plans and the
the internal logs of the database so
having too many indexes will degrade
performance even without dead logs but
dead logs in the in the in the next
tables are sort of the the worst case
for that when optimizing a database
there are two different things you can
optimize for do you want to tell us
something about that
yeah good point the there are basically
two different kinds of things you do
with databases many applications one
thing is putting day to a data into it
and occasionally retrieving data the
other is running huge reports on it only
reading reading reading reading and
putting much load on the database
reading it the first thing is called
OLTP online transactional processing and
this is sort of what you think of if you
have an interactive application like
you log into Amazon then the books are
still probably stored in the database I
don't know but I'd expect them to be
and so you when you do a query some
books the books are restored and the
details are retrieved from the database
and your cart is probably stored in the
database somewhere if you order
something in store in the tables it's
all single row insert and very low slow
scale retrieval but often times in the
back office you have very very different
kinds of things they they will run huge
reports on how many customers bought
what kinds of books today to optimize
their advertising or to create and
prognosis for the revenue that kind of
thing which does huge queries over
millions of rows in the database and
those two are they will require very
different tuning the database because
they want very different um
optimizations online transactional
processing you will need few indexes
most of the time data is stored and
storing the data quickly is very
important but quick response times
deterministic quick response times are
very important whereas in this
back-office part with the huge queries
that code
that's called OLAP online analytical
processing related to data warehousing
there you have huge queries for huge
reports that may run several minutes and
well basically bring the database server
into saturation during that time which
means this one query takes up a hundred
percent of the resource of the database
server while it was running
he won't you don't want to have that
kind of impact on the while while people
are working with Amazon want to buy
books and then cannot buy the books
because one of those reports is running
and you also have very different kinds
of indexes that you weren't they're very
specialized for those kinds of reports
so typically you end up with two
replicated databases one is optimized
optimized for read performance and
another one is optimized for write
performance if you need that right
yes exactly that's what's one typical
architectural approach to have to day
basis one for the m4 OLTP one for OLAP
and then have database replication from
the OTP into the OLAP or the data
warehouse typically during night time or
low load hours if you have those so
another huge topic I guess is security
so what can I do in my database to
ensure certain security things Oh
security is as always a big topic first
of all well the different different
parts of security one is taking care to
be making difficult for people to who
work for your own company to spy on spy
out data the database administrators
people working on the data center
because typically data is exchanged
between the application and the database
in a non encrypted format which is
usually not an issue if the if it's
inside the data center you have secure
Network lines it is however an issue if
you have or potentially an issue if you
have data running if you access the
database from outside the the data
center or even over the internet that
usually not a good idea because the data
is goes unencrypted and passwords may go
clear-text armed for that it is a better
idea to have to have three-tier
architecture with us with an application
server running in the in the data center
and having a secure network between the
application server and the database this
is sort of the raw wire espionage thing
which is good to keep in mind but is not
such a big issue in practice most of the
time and at another level it's important
to fine tune or to manage who may access
which data in the database or modify
what data in the database you want to
provide different users with different
permissions on the database um and for
that databases come with user management
of their own and it's quite
sophisticated usually the database
servers support users they
user groups even and you can assign them
rights saying this user may or this
everyone in this group may insert data
into the person table or may read data
from the person table but or you can
even be more fine-grained by saying can
read all columns in the person table
except for the income column which is
confidential or some databases even have
data-driven authorization by by
specifying a user a debit user can read
data from the person from the employee
table um for all those rows with an
income of less than $30,000 a year or
for employees whose job this job title
is not manager this is fight quite
fine-grained and it's good as far as it
goes but there are but it's not widely
used nowadays for many applications I'll
go to that right away there's a
different model now but and that is the
model of having oh well no this first
approach is basically having a one
database user per human user of the of
the system so in the you administer do
you have a ministration of the users and
the permissions in the database and if I
log into the application with my name
are no and a password
these are passed through to the database
and the application logs into the
database using the credentials I
provided at login this has the benefit
of that it that it permits traceability
and logging in the database and this is
sort of the the traditional approach for
which databases are or optimized another
approach is to have an application
server in between and provide a
technical user or have the database
provide a technical user generic user to
the application server and all excess
goes through this to one generic user
and all the permission checking is done
in the application server which means
that as long as the application server
is not compromised there's no problem
and the entire responsibility lies with
the application server the downside of
this is that you have no traceability in
the database
who accessed what all this logging is
not useful anymore the upside is that
you can have things like connection
pools in the application server which
means that while creating a connection
to the database is an important thing
expensive thing and a connection costs
lots of resources and it takes some time
to create so application servers create
a pool of database connections in
advance and pool that and whenever
someone uses it needs one it's returned
from this pool and when this when it's
been its productions finished basically
it goes back to the pool which means you
need fewer transactions if you need
fewer connections at the same time
another benefit is that you have better
integrations with single sign-on systems
and you can have well your applications
nowadays need to know about permissions
anyway so it's not sufficient to have
the permissions in the database you need
having the applications who have any way
to do gray out menu items or whatever in
the user interface not a huge problem
and these kinds of systems might be SQL
injection do you want to tell us
something about that sequent action is
based on the way many applications are
implemented today by using string
concatenation to create their sequel
on-the-fly one example
well let's say someone logs in and you
have have a select statement to check
authorization by things like select
asterisk from user where user ID or a
user name equals quote and the name that
was entered in the in the login dialog
quote and password equals quote and then
the password that was entered in the
login dialog and then you had another
quote and send it to the database and if
you find a row then you know that the
user is permitted to to access the
system if you don't find a row you know
the login was invalid now if if you
enter quote or one
wills one or quote or quote quote equals
quote um into the password field then
you and then this leads to another valid
sequel statement but this equals
statement basically accesses any account
because in the where clause we have one
equals one so secret injection is based
on entering sequel code into in the user
interface and if the application is
programmed in securely by accusing
string concatenation in an unsafe way to
create the where clauses then the
application can be compromised
there are ways around this many
libraries nowadays are intrinsically
secure against that prepared statements
and Java for example are safe against
this but still it's it's good to keep in
mind that's all for security now so now
let's maybe have a look for the
different database tools ok well I'll be
quite brief here there is a wide range
of database products out there and well
you can look at the data sheets of the
vendors if you want to compare them and
anyway in most in Menace's in many
companies there is one global decision
for one database tool anyway the sequel
standard is what is common to all of
them they all have they're all implement
the sequel standard to different degree
but quite widely by now they have their
specific enhancements of the sequel
standard that add on certain special
syntax it's used to be important it's
not that important anymore to have this
these syntactic add-ons but what is
really really important and is usually
the key thing to to make it is making
the decision is the administration tools
around the database for example user
administration tablespace administration
or performance tuning support
replication support but also support for
doing hot backups that is doing and
making a backup of the database while it
is still in use without compromising the
consistency of the backup running all
kinds of Diagnostics that kind of thing
is very important in enterprises and
those
things are really what differentiates
commercial products from open source
products much of the time and this is
where the commercial products have
different specialties that's one
important thing to look at another thing
is scalability how fast the database out
of the box which is interesting where it
is interesting to notice that for
example my sequel is very fast compared
to much of the bigger databases
especially if you have mainly maybe have
read access so this is something to
really take a look at um but then
another thing is to look at how well
this performance scales up if you want
if you have database of a terabyte it's
very different issue from fast
performance for small databases support
for clustering having several databases
that act as a single database it's
another thing that goes into this
performance and cluster and and
scalability thing and then the all these
operational things like like replication
having high availability support and
service level agreements that support
these but then you also have special
features that may or may not be useful
for your application many databases now
have some kind of xml query support that
is they can retrieve they can return
data as XML they have custom types
custom objects they have stored
procedures are stored procedures yeah
there's a lot of debate going on around
stored procedures some people say some
purists say they're not stupid
understand that you shouldn't use them
and anyway if you're a Java programmer
or c-sharp programmer you're not very
much in touch with them much of the time
you can't do anything in Java and
c-sharp so what are stop procedures a
good point stored procedures are our
code our procedures that are stored
inside the database in some kind of
proprietary language pl/sql for oracle
for example and these this code is
executed inside the database and what
procedures basically move program logic
to the database which is bad for things
like refactoring for maintainability
that kind of thing but it's very good
for performance this is basically the
trade-off behind stored procedures and
if you need them you'll you'll know that
and I'm basically calling a start
procedure from an SQL query yes well the
syntax is not standardized different
databases have different dialects
different syntax for calling the stored
procedures but yes basically you call it
from SQL or via an API those are the two
two approaches that are there so now we
heard how databases are implemented in
general how would I make use of them in
my actual system yeah well this sort of
drives as the architectural issues we it
is a wide area I'll just start by
talking about the things I that come to
my mind first of all there is object
relational mapper they are basically
libraries or frameworks that make it
easy or easier to get objects and all
the object specific way of thinking like
references collections Maps inheritance
into relation into a relational database
that has none of these things and
retrieve data from a relational database
into these kind of object things we're
going to have a dedicated episode on
object relational mapping so I'll not go
into those very much here but if you
start thinking about the system
architecture um with the database the
first thing to keep in mind really is
the different roles of people who are
deal with the database there are at
least four roles for different kinds of
people who deal with the database in a
development effort the first role is the
users of the database that is the
programmers those are usually the first
that come to our mind the people who
write the queries who write the the
modification code who had the update the
update the insert statements call the
stored procedures who write the store
procedures all that kind of thing
this is basically using the database
it's very important obviously but it's
not the only role at the other end of
the spectrum is the database
administrator he's the guy who takes
care of how many disks in what kind of
raid arrays are available how fast data
and the database grows and well he's the
guy who orders a new disk array of the
Oh disk arrays tend to become full he's
the guy who monitors performance all
that kind of thing a whole different
approach how different view onto the
database and it's it's a good idea to to
talk to the system to the database
administrators to the system
administrators next time you develop a
database system it'll open your eyes and
you'll get a whole different view and
it's important to well it's a good idea
to have the the the database
administrators perspective in mind if
you write it if you write a system that
uses the database and sort of in between
there's the database design that is the
people who decide what tables what
columns there are what they are called
what how what what relations there are
between them let's the logical database
design and there's the physical database
design which is again distinct from that
which is how are the tables spread
across different table spaces for
example if you have a huge application
in which data runs which all the time
many many rows a day that's a couple of
of million rows every day and the most
frequently used data is the data that of
a current day and it may be good idea to
put the data to split the table look um
physically which can be transparent to
the to the application but to split the
table on to two table spaces based on
the timestamp value and have the data
that is of the current day in one table
and older data in another table that
kind of thing that's physical database
design so those are the four row
of people who deal with the database
wouldn't I use use in that case
materialized views you might want to use
a materialized view depends on what kind
of of queries you have splitting data on
different table spaces that are on
different hard disks arm can be a
significant speed-up in many situations
a lot better than having a materialized
view that isn't the tablescape same
tablespace on the same same disk again
the depending on the on the situation
one or the other may be the better
approach it was just sort of trying to
illustrate the range of things you can
do at the physical level if you have
huge amounts of data and want to
optimize for that but you mentioned
tablespace now what is what is the
tablespace tablespace is well it's the
disk space on which a table is stored
basically it's specific for different
vendors how they manage this basically
every tape role or well every row at
least is on one tablespace typically
every table is in one tablespace and
managing tablespace is predicting the
size of the table spaces that is needed
and maybe even optimizing so they can be
put on different disks so the
performance of the disks is is edit and
increases overall performance that's the
kind of thing you can do by dealing with
table spaces then you've approach that
most systems take at least in the
beginning is to who I have the entire
schema on one tablespace and that's that
so most systems do not really actively
do any physical database design to
optimize performance another thing that
is related to this is this using
different table spaces is distributing
the database itself using clusters again
there are trade-offs there
first of all price of course but leaving
that aside if you have a cluster the key
idea is that the performance should go
up but if you have a cluster that means
that you have distributed locks because
the different the database must still
maintain integrity across the entire
cluster depending on the specialties of
the product it's important to look at
the trade-offs that are involved but
planning to cluster the database is one
way to improve performance differently
an architectural issue something to look
at
maybe even early on because um may
require some effort some rework in the
database design again as with any
optimization you should do that only
after measuring the performance and
obviously it should be part of the
decision making process as some of their
databases to support clustering and
others don't
oh yes of course of course yeah I was I
was assuming if for an enterprise
application you were using an enterprise
scale database system anyway and they do
support clustering but yes of course
this is important part of the
decision-making yes um another thing I
mentioned that already is the
replication thing Oh OLAP versus OLTP or
more generally for different kinds of
uses for the data it may be good idea to
isolate the performance hits by
replicating especially if there is
little load during the night you always
have that kind of thing available hmm
getting closer to the code here right um
there's the decision between having a
three tier and a two tier application
three tier is what's usually done so
it's the modern way of doing things it's
the way we see blue things here which
means you have a server-side application
server that runs in the data center and
all user management of the rosacea
management is in the in the application
server and only the application server
talks to the database sort of more
secure because you can put the
application server in a demilitarized
zone have a firewall between the
applications of the database which makes
it harder to hack the database server
and the to tier approach on the other
hand means that you have logic in the
client and auto logic in stored
procedures stored in the database and
the client application talks directly to
the database which means you have rich
client not a web client which is well
sort of against the trend still there
are very important applications that or
class of applications that use two-tier
architectures for example call center
applications where tens where fractions
of a second in response time are very
important we have few users you have a
controlled environment that kind of
thing to to replicate a two-tier
architecture can be a very good idea
then going even closer to
or well over in more towards the code
the it's a good idea to know the details
of the excess library you used to access
the database you have some kind of
result set you iterate over but
databases nowadays support crawling in
both directions usually using things
called cursors and you can write data to
the cursor directly that kind of thing
is good to know to to know what you can
do and one final thing about the
architecture is one of my favorites
internationalization um why I set a
topic in there and the database design
it's important because using different
encodings has an impact on the number of
bytes that every character needs to
represent it as long as you use one of
the iso character sets
I saw 8859-1 or whatever your the safe
side you have one character or one byte
per character so it's sort of intuitive
but obviously there are limitations with
regards to internationalization you
cannot have kerlick or even Chinese
characters in there so if you want to go
to UTF well if you use utf-16 you have
two bytes per character and the sizing
of the puke the sizing of the database
columns is typically in bytes not in
characters very tricky from the database
perspective it's sort of obvious because
the database needs to reserve some some
amount of memory and that invites but um
usually of sixteen you'd have you need
to make all your watch our columns
Watchers columns twice the size or if
you use utf-8 which is a variable length
encoding for seven bits esky you have
one byte per character but if you have m
loads you have two bytes per character
and for more exotic characters you have
up to six bytes per character so if you
use it if you're planning for an
internationalization application it's
important to think up front what kinds
of characters you want to support how do
you plan to size your database columns
and then you can you need to size in
accordingly and then only after you did
that um you should actually set up the
database to use the encoding you chose
it's very tricky and often times is not
noticed until late in the cycle because
it's non-obvious
even during testing you would need to
test the database with kirill 'ok
strings of love big size which may or
may not be a test case depending on the
technical expertise of the people
writing the test cases okay so um i
guess we're done right yes I think we
basically covered most things there is
however one story I would like to share
with our listeners which is my favorite
see my favorite database driver back and
again I'm not going to tell to tell you
what kind of product it was because the
sleeve kind of bugs are present for for
many different products this product is
not not worse than all of the others but
it's one of the really big players in
the game so there was this this
application I was writing on a huge time
pressure and it started started behaving
weird so I spent two days I think it was
debugging the database driver until I
found that if you used Java prepared
statements using a better update and had
a database table that had two big
decimals and one varchar' no it was two
varchar columns and one big decimal
column I think and you did in the batch
update you did two updates using
specific strings then for the third
update um the upper limit of the big
decimal column went down to less than a
hundred regardless of the constraints
who actually had stored in the database
and all these conditions actually needed
to be present for the back to turn up it
was really weird but after I found it
was easy to work around it
I'm trying to I'm telling you this is
don't take anything for granted
databases are there databases are very
very reliable they're excellent products
and it's good to rely on them but if
there is a problem think out of the box
the database may be part of the problem
even the database driver may be part of
the problem and this kind of mindset has
helped me in lots of projects okay so um
do we want to do a short wrap-up let me
see um databases are cool databases are
here they're here to stay
databases are very very useful and
despite what I said they are often the
best trade-off - for for a way to store
data why are they so predominant I think
one of the key things is there is a very
very well understood and well standard
IEEE standard for the sequel language
they're sort of interoperable well no
not the database our table but we have
see if you know sequel you can deal with
any of the databases they're more or
less interchangeable from the developers
perspective you have they're very mature
technology you have special solutions
for many special problems like stored
procedures like replication you have
very good administration tools obviously
they are very widely used which makes it
sort of self-perpetuating because they
are widely used that means there are
further developed they are well-known
the money goes there etc that's why they
sort of keep being used um
and well to be honest they are extremely
well optimized by now so basically they
are pretty fast but faster than anything
you can write anyway at least in one of
the typical development projects okay so
thanks ah no thanks bad
what's pleasure talking to you about
databases all right
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team @ su radio net or if it's
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie Crowl and
the Potts a music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle